DELICIOUS IN DUNGEON
《迷宫饭》
This one isn't dead. Just paralyzed.
这个人还没死 只是麻痹了而已
On this floor, of all places? Can you revive him?
在这层吗？你能治好吗？
Not sure.
不确定
Good. Looks like you're revived.
很好 看来你被治好了
We were wiped out?
我们的队伍原本全灭了？
My necklace is gone.
我的项链不见了
My coins are gone, too.
我的金币也消失了
And so are all the jewels.
连宝石也不见踪影
We lost some of our belongings.
我们遗失了部分所有物
Do you know anything about it?
你知道些什么吗？
No doubt about it. They were taken out by Treasure Bugs.
他们一定是被宝物虫袭击 错不了
Shh!
嘘
Nah, we don't know a thing.
天晓得 我们也不知道
We found you all lined up nicely on the ground.
你们在这排成一列倒下了
Some folks must have passed here before we did.
想必有其他人在我们来之前通过吧
A strand of hair.
一缕头发
It's magic to ward off ghosts.
是驱除幽灵的魔法
Someone definitely came in contact with us.
看来确实有人与我们接触过
An elf…
精灵
A tall-man…
长身人
A half-foot… And a dwarf.
半身人还有矮人
They had a meal here.
他们曾在这里吃过饭
A meal?
吃饭？
They sure have some nerve.
他们的神经也太大条了吧
Let's go after them.
我们追上去
Hold up.
等一下
We're not a charity, you know.
我们可不是做慈善的
Here.
拿去
Thanks.
谢了
Why didn't you tell them?
为什么不告诉他们真相？
It's simple.
这还用问吗？
The more corpses, the better.
尸体当然是越多越好
I really want to wash my hair soon.
差不多想洗头了
You'll feel refreshed if you crop your hair.
剃掉头发就清爽多了
There you go again, saying mean things.
你又说那种欺负人的话
Don't you want to wash your beard as well, Senshi?
先西也想洗胡子吧？
How long has it been since you last washed it?
你究竟是从何时开始没洗过？
Let's give it a wash right now!
现在就来洗吧
Your hair plays an important role in magic, too.
毛发对于魔法而言也相当重要
Taking care of it is like warm-up.
保养毛发就像是热身运动
With your beard like that, my support magic might not work on you.
我的辅助魔法 可能会对你的胡子无效喔
That would be just great.
那真是再好不过
Right! I have really nice soap.
对了 我有块不错的香皂
I'll wash your beard with it and braid it!
帮你把胡子洗干净 然后编成辫子吧
Huh? I can't find it.
奇怪 怎么找不到？
Right, that day…
对了 就在那天…
No way! It was so expensive, though!
不会吧 那个超贵的耶
Let's go.
我们走吧
On the fourth basement floor,
地下四层
there is a lake formed by underground water
从凹陷岩盘流出的地下水
flowing through carved-out bedrock.
形成了一片湖泊
The magic-infused water emits a faint glow,
蕴含魔力的水发出微弱的光芒
and far in the depths of the water,
在遥远的湖底看得到城堡周围的小镇
the castle town can be seen like a wavering illusion.
正如梦似幻地摇曳着
How do you usually explore the fourth floor, Senshi?
先西平常是怎么探索第四层的？
I fish and set traps around here.
老夫会在这附近钓鱼或设陷阱
That's about it.
大概就这些吧
How do you fellows get through this place?
你们打算怎么往前走？
With magic, of course.
当然是用魔法了
I use this to do this and…
把这个像这样 然后…
There!
好
We walk across on water.
这下我们就能在水面上行走了
N…
不…
N…?
“不”？
No!
不要
-No! -No need to get so upset.
-不要 -你用不着如此不情愿吧
-This won't work.
-这下没办法了
Let's tie a rope around him and drag him along.
用绳子绑住 再拖着他走吧
No.
不行
Put a spell on him while I'm holding him down.
趁我压制住他的时候 快点施魔法
-What? -With his armor--
-什么？ -要身穿铠甲…
With his armor, it's the only way to get him across the water.
要穿着铠甲越过湖 只有这个方法可行
It's too dangerous to take a boat.
坐船太危险了
People easily fall for the path of ease.
人总是容易堕落 走上安逸的道路
It takes only a moment to get rusty, but it takes a long, long time to--
道理就像生锈只需一瞬间 但重新磨亮则要很长的…
There!
看我的
See? It wasn't such a big deal, was it?
看吧 这又没什么 不是吗？
Y-You…!
你这家伙
I don't get it. Why do you hate magic so much?
我真的不懂 这有什么好抗拒的？
You people are too casual when it comes to using magic.
你们动不动就爱施魔法
That's something I don't understand.
老夫才搞不懂你们在想什么呢
Now, now.
好啦 没关系
What's done is done.
木已成舟 多说无益
You might actually like it.
说不定你会很中意呢
-Huh?
-什么？
W-Why?
为什么？
Why isn't my magic working as well as it should?
为何效力这么弱？
This must be it.
是因为这个吧
Ugh, is this an insulator?
天啊 这什么？是绝缘体吗？
It's soaked with the oils and blood of various monsters.
许多魔物的油脂与血液都渗透进去了
Ew!
好恶心
Wash it off quickly!
快点洗干净吧
I'm not sure if it will come off with just water…
看来很难用水洗掉…
No need.
没有必要
I will get across the water in my own way.
老夫要用自己的方式渡水
Huh?
什么？
Are you gonna build a boat?
你想动手做一艘船吗？
You'll sink like a stone in no time.
那你会立刻下沉 跟海藻作伴耶
No, he must have some amazing plan.
不 他必定是有什么妙计
You sure have a lot of confidence in him.
为何对他如此信赖啊？
I don't get it.
我无法理解
Watch me.
你们看着吧
-Is that the outer shell of a Mimic? -Shh!
-那是宝箱怪的壳？ -安静
A Kelpie!
水栖马
Watch out! Get back!
危险 快退后
It's fine. It's harmless.
没事的 它不会害人
Anne is a horse that always shows up whenever I fish.
老夫钓鱼时安努都会主动靠近
Anne?
安努？
For a while now, I've been wondering if I could use her to get across the lake.
老夫从以前就在想 是不是能靠它越过这片湖
-What?
-什么？
Perhaps I can use the Mimic's shell to steer her somehow.
也许能用宝箱怪的壳顺利诱导它
T-That's…
那也未免…
so cool!
太棒了吧
THIS SCREAMS ADVENTURE
（经典冒险）
I'm against it.
我反对
I think it'd be more practical to use its guts to make a float.
拿它的内脏做浮袋还比较有用
H-How can you say that?
你怎么能说这种话？
How cruel of you!
你太残忍了吧
Monsters are dangerous.
魔物毕竟是危险生物
Especially ones that are charming.
尤其是讨喜的类型
Kelpies make you lower your guard and entice you into the water.
水栖马会先使人大意 再将对方拖进水中
You can never know what's going on in a monster's mind.
我们绝对无法察觉魔物的真正想法
I've known Anne for a long time, just like I've known the golems.
安努与巨魔像一样 和老夫是老交情了
I know her much better than you.
老夫比你还要了解它
Why does everyone have a soft spot for mammals
为什么大家对哺乳类特别宽容？
when they won't let me grow a Man-eating Plant?
明明不让我栽培食人植物
Do you really not know why?
你是真的搞不懂理由吗？
Let's go, Anne!
我们走吧 安努
-Senshi!
-先西
-Marcille! -Huh?
-玛露希尔 -什么？
Anne…
安努…
Stop it, Anne!
住手啊 安努
Laios!
莱欧斯
Forgive me, Anne.
原谅老夫 安努
No way.
不会吧
No way!
这是骗人的吧
Please no!
千万不要啊
So, she was waiting for me to get on her back?
所以安努一直在等 老夫骑到它的背上？
But she could've attacked me whenever she wanted.
但它明明随时都能攻击老夫
I don't know.
谁知道
There's no knowing what a monster is thinking.
魔物的想法难以理解
I don't understand.
老夫不懂
I don't understand at all.
完全不懂
You must be cold.
很冷吧？
I'll start a fire right now.
我现在就生火
Hey!
我说你啊
You were that fond of her, and now you're going to eat her?
之前那么疼爱这匹马 现在却要吃掉它？
Unbelievable.
真不敢相信
Why, though?
为什么？
Can I help?
需要帮忙吗？
No.
不用
I'll do it on my own.
老夫一个人来就好
Hey.
我问你
Can I get some of the fat?
可以分一点油脂给我吗？
What brought this on?
你会这样还真是少见呢
Just an idea.
我想到一个好主意
What on earth are we doing here?
我们到底是来做什么的？
Chilchuck.
奇尔查克
Something is floating over there.
那边好像有东西浮在水面上
It better not be people.
是人类就糟了
Let's go and take a look.
我们去看看吧
What? I'd rather not.
什么？真不想去
What are these white things?
这些白白的是什么？
It's grain.
是大麦
Looks like it's been spilled.
看来是里头的东西掉出来了
And here are the owners.
持有者也在这呢
Let's draw them out of the water.
将他们打捞到陆地上吧
What is it?
怎么了？
Doesn't his face seem familiar?
你不觉得好像在哪里看过这张脸吗？
Nope.
没看过
Oh, I know this kobold!
哦 这个狗头人我倒见过
We found him dead on the third basement floor.
之前倒在地下三层
How did they get ahead of us?
我们为何会被他们超前？
So, they met a Mermaid and killed each other.
所以说他们跟人鱼同归于尽了啊
The poor… things…
真是可怜
Chilchuck?
奇尔查克？
Chil! Chilchuck!
奇尔 奇尔查克
Chil!
奇尔
They never let me finish the song,
那些人鱼又没听我唱到最后
even though I took the trouble of remembering it.
亏我好不容易才记住的
That should do it.
这样就行了
We shouldn't let the scattered grain go to waste.
散落出来的大麦好浪费啊
Let's gather the grain for them.
替他们收集起来吧
That's going too far.
太啰嗦了吧
Then let's take them for ourselves.
不然我们拿走好了
It'll make Marcille happy.
玛露希尔会很开心的
Poor Marcille.
可怜的玛露希尔
No!
不行
I didn't say anything yet.
我什么都还没说耶
You promised not to go for demi-humans!
不是说好不对亚人类型的出手吗？
Demi-humans…
亚人…
What are they?
什么算亚人？
What do you mean?
你在说什么啊？
Mermaids come in different forms.
人鱼有分种类
Some are mammals, while others are more like fish.
分别是哺乳类跟鱼类
This one's in the fish category.
这算是鱼类那种
It lays eggs, so it doesn't have a belly button or nipples.
因为会产卵 所以没有肚脐跟乳头
Instead, it has gills.
而且还有鳃
They're farther removed from humans than cows or pigs.
在生物种类上 比牛或猪还要离人类更远
What?
什么？
-No way! -What?!
-就是不行 -什么？
Why, though?
哪里不行？
Why can we eat cow but not a Fish-man?
告诉我牛可以吃 但鱼人不能吃的理由
It just doesn't feel right.
就是会觉得情感上无法接受
Feel?
情感？
Feel, huh?
是因为情感喔？
They're still at it.
他们居然还在弄
I'm starting to feel hungry, so how about we whip something up?
肚子也饿了 我们先来做饭吧
Throw the grains in water and put it over a fire.
将大麦放进水里 再生火加热
Toss in some flaked Mimic and waterweeds, then--
放入剥成丝的宝箱怪肉与水草…
Wait a minute.
等一下
That's the stuff that was growing on the Fish-man's head.
那些是长在鱼人头上的东西吧？
Yeah, but this is just a normal plant.
对 但这些就只是普通的植物
The Fish-men use it to camouflage.
被鱼人拿来拟态用
Without it, they'd look even more fishy.
没水草的话 看起来就更像鱼了
Does it still upset your feelings?
这个你情感上也无法接受吗？
This is starting to become a bother.
事情开始变得麻烦了
Fine. Have it your way.
好啦 随你高兴
I think I might've made an error in judgment just now.
总觉得刚才好像下错判断了
All right. It's ready.
好 完成了
PORRIDGE WITH SCATTERED BARLEY
（附近散落的大麦杂炊粥）
Marcille, Senshi, let's have lunch.
玛露希尔、先西 来吃午餐吧
Is it that time already?
已经这个时间啦？
Where did you manage to find some grains?
你从哪弄来的大麦？
I scavenged them from the fallen adventurers over there.
我捡了死在那边的冒险者弄掉的
What on earth were you thinking?
你在搞什么啊？
Good question. I knew Marcille wouldn't disappoint.
说得没错 不愧是玛露希尔
But you already cooked them, so.
算了 既然煮好也只能吃了
I'll dig right in!
我要开动了
Hmm, there's a pop in the texture.
好像有颗粒的口感
What is it?
这是什么？
Probably fish eggs.
是鱼卵吧
They must've been on the water weeds.
应该是附着在水草上了
It tastes good.
真好吃
I know, right?
很好吃吧？
I'm glad I added them.
幸好有放进去
Come with me.
你给我过来
Hey!
我问你
Those were a Fish-man's eggs, weren't they?
那是鱼人的卵吧？
I've heard Fish-men have a habit of laying their eggs on waterweeds
我听说过鱼人会产卵在头上的水草
that they wear on their heads to protect them or something!
那是保护鱼卵的习性之类的
What's the matter?
怎么了？
Marcille.
玛露希尔
Does it taste good?
那个好吃吗？
Yeah!
好吃
Senshi.
先西
This is for you.
这个给你
I made soap using the Kelpie's fat.
我用水栖马的油脂做了肥皂
Kelpie's fat is often used as hair oil,
水栖马的油脂是相当好的发油
but it can also be used for clothes and dishes.
也能用在衣服或餐具上
Can I use it right now?
现在马上能用吗？
It's still being saponified, so I'm not sure.
还在皂化中 我也不确定
I want to give it a try.
老夫想马上用
You put a lot of effort into making it, right?
这是你花工夫做的吧？
Okay.
好
Thank goodness!
太好了
Now, we can move ahead together.
这样就能一起往前走了
I see.
原来如此
Now that it's come to this, I've realized something.
这样试过后 老夫发现了一件事
Walking on water actually feels quite nice.
走在水面上让人心情愉悦呢
Thank you, Marcille.
谢谢你啊 玛露希尔
Some soap got into my eye.
肥皂跑进眼睛里了
Leave this to me.
交给我吧
I'll wipe them out!
我来一口气解决掉
Don't!
住手
-Watch out! -Ow!
-危险 -好痛
I told you not to!
不是叫你住手吗？
An underwater explosion kills too many of them!
在水中爆破就杀过头了
What?
什么？
These Blade Fish can be stewed, grilled, steamed,
这些刃鱼可用来炖煮、烧烤、闷蒸
dried, smoked, or eaten raw.
做成鱼干、烟熏、生吃
They're delicious no matter how you prepare them.
怎么料理都好吃
But they're a food source for other monsters as well.
但同时也是其他魔物的粮食
If their population decreases, it could disrupt the dungeon's ecosystem.
数量减少会影响迷宫的生态系
So you should get them one at a time.
要杀就一只一只瞄准
What? You're asking too much!
什么？人家办不到啦
Now that I think about it,
这么说来
it seems like there are fewer mid-sized monsters around than usual.
中型魔物似乎比平时还少
See?
看吧
I can't just go easy on them, though.
我怎么可以手下留情
Not when they're trying to kill us.
对方也想要取我们的命耶
If anything, there are more Blade Fish than usual.
刃鱼明明比平常还多
I don't think there's anything to be concerned about.
根本不需要担心吧
But what if the monsters end up starving?
要是以后吃不到了怎么办？
I don't want to die just to protect their ecosystem!
我不想为了保护魔物的生态系而死
You people are too quick to take the easy path.
你们都只想用简单的方法做事
What? Then you should try taking them out one by one.
那是什么话 先西？ 那你一只一只杀给我看啊
It's hard, you know!
这很不容易耶
You should think about the ecosystem more…
老夫是要你多为生态系着想…
What's going on?
怎么了？
Senshi!
先西
What was that all about? They just passed by us.
怎么回事？那些家伙直接越过我们了
Are you hurt?
有没有受伤？
Senshi?
先西？
Something is approaching.
有东西正在靠近
What?
什么？
You're kidding, right?
不会吧？
It's way too huge!
这也太大了
A squid?
乌贼？
Or is it an octopus?
还是章鱼？
It's a Kraken!
是克拉肯
It's a big monster to begin with,
它本来就是大型魔物
but this one's a few times larger than the usual ones!
这只比普通的大上好几倍
It's so cool!
好帅气
What do we do?
要怎么办？
If we act rashly, it's gonna get us!
随意行动会被干掉的
We'll draw its attention!
我们去引开它
I'm counting on you, Marcille.
交给你了 玛露希尔
Magic again?
又要用魔法吗？
Relax. I'll strike it this time.
你放心 这次会打中它
Here it comes!
来了
Don't stop running!
不要停下脚步
Right there!
这里
I did it!
成功了
No way! It didn't take a hit!
不会吧 完全没用
Using a weapon on it will only slice through its outer skin at most.
用武器顶多只能伤它的一层外皮
There must be magic I can use…
有没有什么魔法能用？
Marcille!
玛露希尔
-Use your magic again. -What?
-拜托你再施一次魔法 -什么？
I can't pull off such a powerful magic in quick succession.
我无法连续施放如此大型的魔法
No.
不
This will do.
用这个
I mean, this is your first encounter with a Kraken, right?
说起来你是第一次看到克拉肯吧？
Do you even know what kind of monster it is?
你了解这种魔物吗？
-I don't. -What?
-不了解 -什么？
I don't know much about Krakens,
克拉肯的事老夫是不懂
but I have cleaned squids and octopuses before.
但乌贼跟章鱼老夫倒是有宰杀过
Watch out, Marcille!
小心 玛露希尔
It's heading your way!
它过去你那边了
Water-Walk!
水上步行
To kill a squid or an octopus,
杀乌贼跟章鱼时
stab it right between the eyes!
要瞄准眼睛之间
Amazing.
好厉害啊
Huh?
奇怪
Where's Laios?
莱欧斯呢？
Hey. I'm over here.
喂 我在这里
Looks like this creature was devouring all the medium-sized monsters.
看来是这家伙在狂吃中型魔物
Both of you, come here.
你们两个 过来一下
You should try cleaning a cephalopod at least once.
你们应该试着处理一次海鲜肉
Stab squids and octopuses here to kill them neatly.
乌贼跟章鱼只要刺这里就能顺利宰杀
Do squids and octopuses taste good?
乌贼跟章鱼好吃吗？
No way! You've never tried them?
不会吧 你没吃过？
They taste really good, you know!
那真的很好吃耶
You can stew, grill, steam, dry, smoke, or even enjoy them raw.
炖煮、烧烤、闷蒸 做成干货、烟熏、生吃
They really taste great no matter how you cook them!
那些真的怎么料理都好吃
I know a good place, so I'll show you there next time.
我知道一间不错的店 下次告诉你
Can't I try one now?
现在吃不行吗？
I dug my own grave!
我自掘坟墓
Wow, this is so weird!
天啊 还真是奇特
How do I eat this?
这要怎么吃？
Let's try salting it.
总之先洒点盐吧
-It stinks. -Well, well!
-好臭啊 -怎么会？
It tastes awfully bitter.
好可怕的苦味
It's making my mouth tingle.
让我嘴巴发麻
Marcille, do you really eat this in various dishes?
玛露希尔 你会吃这玩意儿的各种料理？
No, I don't! That's a weird misunderstanding!
不是 没有啦 不要产生奇怪的误会
How marvelous!
真是不得了
A big parasite for a big monster!
原来大型魔物的寄生虫也很大啊
Ew, disgusting!
讨厌 好恶心
Throw it away now!
现在马上丢掉啦
What's all the fuss about?
这有什么好大叫的？
Most creatures have parasitic worms inside them.
生物本来就会有寄生虫
And many of them end up in our meals, too.
而且很多都会混进料理里面
You didn't have to tell me that!
不用特地说出来啦
Well, if we cook it, we should be able to eat this as well.
所以这只料理过后也能吃吧
No!
不要
That's one way of looking at it.
那种想法也说得通
I said no!
我说不要
Let's try broiling these with some sauce.
这个沾上酱汁烤一烤吧
It's upsetting how amazing it smells!
烤出来的味道却很香 气死人了
It's done!
完成
BROILED AND GLAZED GIANT PARASITIC WORM
（巨型寄生虫的酱烧与原味肉串）
It's good!
好美味
I can't quite put it into words, but it's really soft and delicious!
我不太会形容 但口感松软 非常好吃
It's got a bit of a slime, but it's quite meaty.
稍微有点黏黏的 可是肉很厚实
I-It's good.
真的好吃耶
Not bad.
还不错
This has a delicious taste that's unlike your typical fish.
有着不同于普通鱼类的美味
Isn't it even better than squid or octopus?
这应该比乌贼跟章鱼好吃吧？
That's not…
才没有那回事…
true, probably.
大概吧
I'm pretty sure this would be delicious, no matter how you prepare it as well.
不过感觉这种肉怎么料理都好吃
I had a bite of it raw, but it went down nicely.
我生吃了几口也没有腥味
Hold on, you ate it raw?
等一下 你生吃了吗？
Just a little.
一点点而已
It was already dead, so it should be fine.
已经死了 没关系啦
The fish are eating the Kraken.
鱼在吃克拉肯耶
That should help the medium-sized monsters slowly come back.
这么一来 中型魔物的数量 也会慢慢恢复吧
My stomach…
我的胃…
Ow…
好痛
What's the matter? Are you okay?
怎么了？没事吧？
Well, well…
这是…
It's just as I thought.
果不其然
Laios, what you have is the parasite that was inside the giant parasitic worm.
莱欧斯 你吃进了 巨大寄生虫体内的寄生虫
It's the same kind you find in your average fish, too.
普通鱼类上也经常会有
I spotted one when I was cleaning the big worm.
老夫在切鱼肉的时候看过
It can't be…
怎么会…
It won't parasite on a human,
虽然不会寄生在人类身上
but it does make a hole in your stomach, which can be very painful.
但会在胃开洞 可能很痛苦
All you can do is wait for it to die.
只能等虫子死掉了
I think I might die first.
我可能会先死吧
Why not throw a healing spell on him every now and then?
你就不时替他施治愈魔法吧
Good idea.
就那么办
But I see now.
不过老夫领悟了一件事
The Fish-men eat the Blade Fish,
鱼人吃刃鱼
and the Kraken eats the Fish-men.
克拉肯吃鱼人
We took down the Kraken,
而我们打倒克拉肯
and the little fish feast on its flesh.
小鱼们吃其尸体
Laios ate the parasitic worm inside the Kraken,
莱欧斯吃了克拉肯的寄生虫
and the parasite within that worm ended up poking a hole in Laios' stomach.
其体内的寄生虫如今在他胃壁上开洞
I guess it was a little arrogant of me to try to protect the ecosystem.
老夫扬言要保护生态系 但那想法太过傲慢了
Right from the start, we were already a part of the dungeon's circle of life.
我们打从一开始就是迷宫的一部分
Laios attempted to speak,
莱欧斯试图想说点什么
but the excruciating pain and nausea left his mind completely empty.
但他被猛烈的剧痛与反胃感 搞得完全无法思考
The agony, which felt as if knives were slicing through his insides,
体内有如刀割般的痛苦
persisted all night.
持续了一整晚
And he vowed never to eat a parasitic worm raw again.
让他暗自发誓今后再也不生吃寄生虫
Subtitle translation by: Ai Matsuoka
字幕翻译：梁雪莹